Dr Franziskus Kiefer

About Me

Summary I'm a security & cryptography engineer and researcher based in Berlin.

I'm currently heading the cryptography group at Fraunhofer AISEC. Before joining AISEC I was working on Mozilla's cryptography library NSS. I'm interested in everything around applied cryptography, in particular authentication and key exchange protocols, formally verifiable specifications and implementations of cryptographic primitives, and privacy preserving data collection and computation.

Experience

Industry

since 01/2020 **Head of Cryptography Engineering**, Fraunhofer AISEC, Berlin, Germany. applied cryptography research and development

10/2015 - 01/2020 Senior Cryptography/Security Engineer, Mozilla Germany, Berlin, Germany.

NSS maintainer/developer (cryptography library), Formally verified cryptography using F*,
Design & implementation of OS password storage integration for Firefox, Design & implementation of new extension signing mechanism, Design of authentication frameworks, Set up of
NSS CI infrastructure, Fuzzing, Hardware-accelerated AES-GCM implementation

05/2015 - 07/2015 **Security Engineering Intern**, *Mozilla Inc*, San Francisco, USA.

Security Engineering, Implementing referrer policies (https://www.w3.org/TR/referrer-policy/)

 $11/2009 - 10/2012 \quad \textbf{Software Developer}, \ FlexSecure \ GmbH, \ Darmstadt, \ DE.$ Software development (PKI, JEE, Side channel resistant cryptography, Cryptographic protocols

for German electronic identity cards, Smart card profiles), Software evaluation (Common Criteria).

Open Source & Research

since 2018 hacspec, Formal specification language for specifications.

Designing a new formal language for cryptography algorithms in specifications (https://hacs-workshop.github.io/hacspec/)

since 2017 HACL*, Formally verified cryptograhpic library.

Implementation of cryptographic primitives for $HACL^*$ (https://github.com/project-everest/hacl-star)

2009-2012 FlexiProvider / Bouncy Castle, Java CSP.

 $Implementation\ of\ cryptographic\ primitives\ for\ Java\ Cryptographic\ Provider\ FlexiProvider\ and\ BouncyCastle\ (https://github.com/project-everest/hacl-star)$

Education

01/2013-02/2016 **PhD in Applied Cryptography**, University of Surrey, Department of Computing, Guildford, UK.

10/2010-10/2012 M.Sc in Computer Science (with honours), Technische Universität Darmstadt, Department of Computer Science, Darmstadt, DE.

10/2010-10/2012 M.Sc in IT-Security (with honours), Technische Universität Darmstadt, Department of Computer Science, Darmstadt, DE.

10/2007-09/2010 B.Sc in Computer Science (with distinction), Technische Universität Darmstadt, Department of Computer Science, Darmstadt, DE.

08/2006-04/2007 Community Service, University Hospital Rechts der Isar of the Technischen Universität München, Munich, DE.

06/1998-05/2006 Abitur (A-Level), Gymnasium Marianum, Warburg Westf., DE.

PhD thesis

Title Advancements in Password-based Cryptography [8]

Supervisor Dr. Mark Manulis

Languages

German Native Language

English Fluent

Programming

Languages C, C++, Rust, Python, Bash,

JavaScript, Java

Tools Docker, Git, Mercurial, AWS

Portfolio https://github.com/franziskuskiefer

Teaching & Community

Guest Lectures Lectures on secure content transfer on the internet and practical aspects of the web

public key infrastructure at TU Berlin and TU Darmstadt

Thesis Supervision Beyond privacy-aware counting (Bachelor thesis at TU Berlin 2019)

Community Initiator and co-organiser of the Berlin Crypto meetup (https://berlin-crypto.github.io)

Talks

RWC 2018 HACL* in Mozilla Firefox

ISC 2016 Universally Composable Two-Server PAKE

ISC 2015 Oblivious PAKE – Efficient Handling of Password Trials

ESORICS 2014 Zero-Knowledge Password Policy Checks and Verifier-based PAKE

ACNS 2014 Distributed Smooth Projective Hashing and Two-Server PAKE

CryptoForma 2014 Distributed Smooth Projective Hashing and Two-Server PAKE

MFS Seminar 2014 Password-based Authentication for Mobile Browsers

CryptoForma 2013 Oblivious PAKE – Efficient Handling of Password Trials

SAM 2012 Practical Security in E-Mail Applications

Other Interests

Music I play several instruments (drums, guitar, piano).

Outdoor I like hiking, climbing, and mountaineering.

Publications

- [1] Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Franziskus Kiefer, and Pierre-Yves Strub. hacspec: towards verifiable crypto standards. In SSR 2018: Security Standardisation Research, 2018.
- [2] Johannes Braun, Franziskus Kiefer, and Andreas Hülsing. Revocation and Non-repudiation: When the First Destroys the Latter. In *EuroPKI*, volume 8341 of *Lecture Notes in Computer Science*, pages 31–46. Springer-Verlag, 2013.
- [3] Johannes Buchmann, Johannes Braun, Moritz Horsch, Detlef Hühnlein, Franziskus Kiefer, Falko Strenzke, and Alexander Wiesmaier. Towards a mobile eCard Client. In 13. Kryptotaq, page 4, December 2010.
- [4] Changyu Dong and Franziskus Kiefer. Secure set-based policy checking and its application to password registration. In *Cryptology and Network Security* 14th International Conference, CANS 2015, Marrakesh, Morocco, December 10-12, 2015, Proceedings, pages 59-74, 2015.
- [5] Nils Fleischhacker, Felix Günther, Franziskus Kiefer, Mark Manulis, and Bertram Poettering. Pseudorandom Signatures. Cryptology ePrint Archive, Report 2011/673, 2011. http://eprint.iacr.org/.
- [6] Nils Fleischhacker, Felix Günther, Franziskus Kiefer, Mark Manulis, and Bertram Poettering. Pseudorandom Signatures. In *Proceedings of the 8th ACM SIGSAC symposium on Information, computer and communications security*, ASIA CCS '13, pages 107–118, New York, NY, USA, 2013. ACM.
- [7] Franziskus Kiefer. Effiziente Implementierung des PACE- und EAC Protokolls für mobile Geräte. Bachelor thesis, TU Darmstadt, July 2010.
- [8] Franziskus Kiefer. Advancements in Password-based Cryptography. PhD thesis, University of Surrey, 2016.
- [9] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Distributed smooth projective hashing and its application to two-server password authenticated key exchange. In *ACNS'14*, volume 8479 of *Lecture Notes in Computer Science*, pages 199–216. Springer-Verlag, 2014.
- [10] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Zero-knowledge password policy checks and verifier-based PAKE. In ESORICS'14, volume 8713 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pages 295–312. Springer-Verlag, 2014.
- [11] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Oblivious PAKE: efficient handling of password trials. In *Information Security 18th International Conference*, *ISC 2015*, *Trondheim*, *Norway*, *September 9-11*, *2015*, *Proceedings*, pages 191–208, 2015.
- [12] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Blind password registration for two-server password authenticated key exchange and secret sharing protocols. In Information Security 19th International Conference, ISC 2016, Honolulu, HI, USA, September 3-6, 2016, Proceedings, pages 95–114, 2016.
- [13] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Blind password registration for verifier-based PAKE. In *Proceedings of the 3rd ACM International Workshop on ASIA*

- Public-Key Cryptography, AsiaPKC@AsiaCCS, Xi'an, China, May 30 June 03, 2016, pages 39–48, 2016.
- [14] Franziskus Kiefer and Mark Manulis. Universally composable two-server PAKE. In *Information Security 19th International Conference, ISC 2016, Honolulu, HI, USA, September 3-6, 2016, Proceedings*, pages 147–166, 2016.
- [15] Franziskus Kiefer, Alexander Wiesmaier, and Christian Fritz. Practical Security in E-Mail Applications. In *The 2012 International Conference on Security and Management*, pages 138–144, July 2012.
- [16] Mark Manulis, Nils Fleischhacker, Felix Günther, Franziskus Kiefer, and Bertram Poettering. Group Signatures Authentication with Privacy. German Information Security Agency (GISA), 2012. https://www.bsi.bund.de/EN/.
- [17] Mark Manulis, Douglas Stebila, Franziskus Kiefer, and Nick Denham. Secure modular password authentication for the web using channel bindings. *Int. J. Inf. Sec.*, 15(6):597–620, 2016.
- [18] Alex Wiesmaier, Moritz Horsch, Johannes Braun, Franziskus Kiefer, Detlef Hühnlein, Falko Strenzke, and Johannes Buchmann. An efficient mobile PACE implementation. In *Proceedings of the 6th ACM Symposium on Information, Computer and Communications Security*, ASIA CCS '11, pages 176–185, New York, NY, USA, 2011. ACM.